Welcome back to the TRT and Hormone
Optimization YouTube channel and back
with us is Mike Belulkin. Welcome back,
Mike.
>> Hey, thanks for having me back, Dr.
Dvos. Good to see you.
>> Good to see you, too. And welcome back
to the show. Today we wanted to talk
about the FDA expert panel on TRT that
was held very recently and um you wanted
to talk about that and that's very
interesting because uh me as a layman
living in Europe we have heard nothing
about that and before we start maybe uh
let's explain to the viewers um who is
in that panel exactly and what is the
goal of that panel.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So the, you know, so the the
the FDA, the Food and Drug
Administration here in the US, um they
oversee a lot of um you know, a lot of
things, uh you know, u you know,
medicine wise and prescription wise
here. Um so they held a meeting on
December 10th, so just you know, a
couple days before, you know, we're
having this chat. Um, and the purpose
was to kind of revisit what's going on
with testosterone, the labeling of it,
which, you know, which, um, which
dictates the, you can actually prescribe
it. Um, here in the, you know, here in
the US, it's actually a scheduled
medication. So, it has some, uh, uh, you
know, it's a controlled substance. So,
it's on the same list as some as some
uh, you know, drugs that people use to
to get high basically. I mean things
like you know things like opioids and
bzzoazipines and things that can cause
addiction. So it's kind of kind of
strange that it's on that that it's on
that list and it's been for a while. Uh
so that's what they wanted to revisit
here. So you know the FDA uh recently
has some new leadership right. So with
our new administration here with our new
president we have a new uh you know
director of health and human services
RFK you know RFK. um he's seems to be
very protestosterone, pro peptides and
with that there's a new uh you know new
leadership within the FDA. Dr. Macker um
is kind of the new new leader of the
FDA. So he kind of helped put you know
put some of this you know put some of
this together. uh basically you know
they we had I think there were 15 people
total on this panel and it consisted of
clinicians, researchers um we had uh you
know some some government officials
there some of the folks there we had you
know someone who was a CEO of of a
pharmaceutical company and some of these
you know some of these folks also you
know they list their um you know their
conflicts on there so some of them are
also members of boards for some of these
you know some of these pharmaceutical
companies or or testosterone replacement
companies that kind of you know that
kind of thing. So, it was a pretty, you
know, pretty pretty mixed panel of
folks. Um, it was actually a lot of the
talk was a lot better than I thought it
would be. A lot, you know, a lot of
forward thinking stuff. And then kind of
at the end, you know, the the government
officials threw some cold water on all
of it. It seemed like, hey, you know,
we're slowing this thing down. Let's not
get too excited too fast. That's that's
kind of generally, you know, that's kind
of the general um uh the general layout
of what we what we're looking at here.
And the the recording is available on
the FDA website uh or on the FDA uh
YouTube channel I should say. So your
viewers should go you know should go
watch it. It's a pretty pretty good
listen.
>> Sure. And um what has been said exactly
what what is new?
>> What is new? So you know they basically
came out and said um and it was really
interesting that some of them were this
blunt about it. They kind of kind of
said even opening up with the FDA
director, hey you know for the last 40
years we've been kind of wrong about
testosterone. you know, we've been
giving people the wrong idea. Um, you
know, a lot of the warnings that were
out there are now, you know, not only
completely wrong, but the complete
opposite. Things like, you know,
testosterone causes heart disease. Um,
if, you know, several of the panelists
mentioned, not only does it not cause
heart disease, it prevents heart
disease,
>> right? Not only does it not cause
prostate cancer, men who have low
testosterone are more likely to get the
worst kind of prostate cancer. So, it's
really just just kind of the opposite.
um you know some of them were even um
you know laughing during it saying it's
just so ridiculous is that's the way the
way that it's been. Um but things change
slow right so when the government gets
involved and has you know restrictions
on things to undo things can take can
take a long time. Uh you know the
argument there is maybe they shouldn't
have gotten so involved in the first
place. It wouldn't have been a mess to
begin with but here we are. So it does
seem like they're taking some steps to
maybe kind of kind of undo undo some of
this. Uh but some of the biggest topics
were descheduling testosterone. Right.
So for you know much of the United
States is a schedule three drug which
again means it's reported there's a
whole system if your doctor wants to
write you a prescription he has to look
you up and make sure you're not taking
these other drugs. Uh because of that as
soon as you walk into the office and ask
about it they're a little bit skeptical.
You know they look at you with the same
eyes the same guy who's coming in
looking for you know some uh you know
some oxycodone or some Xanax like hey
what do you what do you want this for?
Um and then on top of that there they're
just you know the there's a lack of
education. um uh in the general you know
uh primary care community about how to
how to actually um prescribe this stuff.
Um and that's something else that the
panelists even mentioned too. Um I
believe his doctor Morgan Tyler said
that he was you know he think it's an
embarrassment and a stain on his
generation of medicine that testosterone
is so um you know so maligned and and
just not taught in medical school and
everything that is taught has been the
complete opposite of what's you know
what's actually true and good. Mhm.
>> So that was one of the big things they
want to want to do. Um they also want to
change some of the labeling. So you know
the current labeling has very specific
indications for treatment. Um and one of
them does not include age related
testosterone decline which is the
biggest and most you know uh we have the
biggest impact on health by by
addressing that one thing. So again now
even if you have your doctor who's on
board you go to see him he looks into
the details of this thing quickly
because he only has two minutes to do
this and uh he sees hey you know you
don't actually meet the criteria so you
know sorry see you know maybe next time.
Uh so a lot of people are kind of kind
of falling through the cracks. So you
know many of the panelists advocated for
that as well and said hey that's a big
thing we need to we need to undo. Um
they also wanted to make sure they kind
of push forward and get some of the
other warnings removed. So recently they
removed the um you know the heart
disease warning off of there. They
replaced it with saying there's some
high blood pressure you know risk which
okay all right split the difference
there. We'll take it. But the um you
know the prostate stuff uh the risk of
prostate cancer is just completely
debunked right. I mean it's just not
it's just not a thing. Um but it does
still remain on some of the labeling. So
it does seem like that's going to be
removed. Um but they did they did kind
of highlight highlight that too.
>> Yeah. Sure. and um for for everyday
practice in a TRT clinic um what is
going to change now?
>> That that's a good question. I think for
the most part um it's going to be
business as usual and I think that's
mostly because
the primary care providers that this
would affect the most it they're still
either not going to be interested in
doing it, they're not going to have all
the knowledge to do it and this is going
to be a pretty a pretty slowmoving
thing. I think if they were to, you
know, enact all this stuff tomorrow and
you say, "Hey, it's not scheduled
anymore. We can do it. We've changed the
labeling." Now, you're still down to um
uh, you know, best practices and what
are they actually doing? We're still
going to see primary care doctors trying
to prescribe one shot every two weeks or
even worse, you know, a shot every
month, whereas we know best practice is
probably, you know, at least two or
three divided, you know, divided shots,
dividing a dose for guys. Um and then
there's some you know fear about um
where we want levels to to get to. Um
many of the panelists they seem like
they were pretty again seem like a
pretty forward thinking thinking group.
None of them really mentioned about you
know um levels for symptom resolution or
that or that kind of thing. Um at the
very end a few of them did mention
something about very low levels and that
levels above that resolution might just
be um placebo. So I think two of the
panelists were going back and forth
saying, "Hey, you know that, you know,
based upon the research, we think that
any any um you know, people with very
low symptom or very low testosterone
under a total of 350, they probably get
good symptom resolution. But someone
with levels above that who's getting
symptom resolution, we think it might be
placebo.
>> So hearing things like that, you know,
other people are going to hear that. A
doctor's going to kind of anchor on that
on that kind of thing."
So, I think, you know, back to your, you
know, back to your your question there,
though, I think because of that, people
are still going to seek out good care
and they're still going to want to use
TRT clinics. You're still going to talk
to an expert who's doing this day in and
day out. Um, I think that, you know, the
the the the time for where you can just
easily get this through your primary
care provider and they're doing the, you
know, giving you the best care with it
is still going to be quite a way down
the road, but it's a start. It's a
start. It's the first we've heard about
it in years. So I think that's a good we
have to start somewhere.
>> Mhm. And was it only TRT that was uh
discussed or were there combinations
with other drugs or uh I don't know.
>> Yeah, you know it was it was mostly
mostly talking about TRT. Um one of the
panelists did bring up some of the kind
of you know some of the mixed use things
like trying hCG and some concerns for
you know fertility and young men and all
that all that kind of kind of deal. It
was really very strongly focused on on
testosterone replacement therapy though
and it was nice because you know some of
the panelists are actually clinicians
too and they're doing it day in and day
out so they had some real good insight
and they kind of had the strongest you
know the strongest words about it. Yeah.
very very uh very testosterone focused.
Um good good you know good listen.
>> Mhm. Here in our mainstream media here
in Europe uh everything fitness,
bodybuilding, testosterone, anabolics,
it's all demonized and thrown on the
same heap.
>> Is it the same over there in United
States or is something becoming maybe a
little bit better in mainstream media?
Yeah, I feel like the um testosterone
replacement therapy and hormone
replacement therapy in general has
softened has softened quite a bit. Um it
really depends upon how you how you
catch it though and hear who you hear
talking about it. It's definitely more
accepted. People are even just um even
just hearing how open people are to just
discussing it amongst themselves. It
used to be, you know, 10 years ago a guy
on TRT would be pretty guarded about it.
They don't want to tell anyone. There's
a lot of stigma. There's a lot of, you
know, a lot of judgment. And now people
are telling their friends, hey, you
know, you're looking great, man. What
are you doing? You look like, you know,
you have a new, you know, uh, new kick
in your step here. What's happening with
you? And they and they share that. So, I
think it's there's less and less stigma
there. Um, I think it's just a hard, you
know, it's it's that stigma is having a
harder time dying with the actual
prescribers, though. I think that's the
biggest that's the biggest barrier. And
I think that's probably one of the
reasons we saw this meeting come
forward, too, right? there's a there's a
lot of a lot of clinics doing this kind
of thing and they really have to pay
attention. You know, if so many people
are doing it, what do you know what what
are we missing here?
>> So, it's nice that they that they're
addressing that.
>> The typical things that we discuss on
this channel that a lot of providers uh
do wrong maybe like blocking estrogen or
advising patients to donate blood when
their hematocrit is over 52 53. Uh were
those things discussed? you know, they
didn't really get into it and that would
that would have been interesting, right?
I think that would be um there was uh
you know, there was a gentleman there
from the um uh the AUA, the so
urological society, and he you know, he
said he was very involved in the you
know, in the most recent guidelines and
he was a he was a pretty, you know, he
was um he was very into treating the
patient and not treating the numbers and
a lot of the things he said. It made me
think that the guidelines that they put
forward were purposefully a little bit
vague because they are a little bit
vague. Um, but that allows the clinician
some leeway to kind of treat the patient
and not just not just treat some
numbers. So, I think that was probably
the intent of the thing, especially
seeing, you know, seeing what what this
gentleman who was so deeply involved in
it had to say, but um, I think people
read it, you know, verbatim and now they
take, you know, go to the lowest common
denominator and the biggest, you know,
the biggest fear. Like I think some of
those guidelines talk about donating
blood if you know hematocrits over um uh
55 and people take that as written in
stone and off they go. But that that
stuff was not addressed. They didn't
they didn't talk about that. That would
be that would be nice to hear in a in a
separate one cut kind of some of the um
you know best practice and maybe some
new guidelines.
>> Yeah. here in our European and
especially or more specifically Belgian
mainstream media, uh, your President
Trump is still demonized. He's still a
clown or a bad man or a dangerous
president, whatever. And together with
him goes the same for um um your um
Kennedy, your minister of health, same
thing. He's also demonized or talked
about like he's a mad man because he's
against vaccines, right?
>> Um what what's the general feeling in
the in the media in the United States
there?
>> Yeah. You mean you mean in general about
about RFK?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Um you see you see a mix on it. he
has um I would say you know the uh you
know the Democrat uh party or the you
know the more liberal liberal leaning
folks um I think they hate him just
because he's you know he's he's on the
other side but they have they have a lot
of a lot of negative things to say a lot
of negative things to say about him um I
see a lot of people in healthc care kind
of kind of demonizing him a little bit a
little bit too I I get I get the feeling
those folks that I talked to are also
politically leaning to the you know to
the left also and that has a lot a lot
to do with it. Um, he does say some
fringe stuff like occasionally he'll say
something like, "Oh, you know, I think
you could have maybe phrased that
better. You might have gone a little too
far there." But he also has advisers
that going to pull him back so he's not
going to make, you know, big big crazy
decisions and he's kind of he's kind of
the, you know, the figurehead. Um, and
he's also a huge um patient advocate,
right? I he cares what happens with
people and he's pushing things forward
like this like this idea we see, you
know, we see here. Um, and sometimes
until you shine light on something, you
don't realize that that that it needs to
be changed. Like this thing's been going
on for, you know, these these um this
demonization of testosterone. It's like
40 plus years of stuff going on here.
And finally, you know, finally it comes
back up again. So, I mean, that that
alone gives him gives him some
credibility in my book. Um, I already I
already kind of liked him, though.
>> Yeah. Well, he's looking great for his
age. He's also very much into fitness,
healthy living. He's Yeah, he's a good
ambassador of health example. Right.
>> Right. Right. Right. Yeah. You see some
Yeah. You see the
you see some of these former um uh
heads, you know, and they're kind of
rolling on the stage and they just don't
look, you know, they're not a they're
not a picture of health. It's hard to
it's hard to take what they're saying
seriously. So, yeah, you like to see
someone who's kind of walking the walk.
For sure.
>> Yeah. Uh you've also talked very
recently with the lawyer Rick Collins.
What was his take on all this?
>> Yeah. No, it was great talking to him.
But yeah, so Rick Collins, lot lots of
insight here. Probably the most um he's
probably covered the most cases
surrounding testosterone and steroids
and peptides and the legalities of all
this. I think he was even involved in
the, you know, the Balco case with the,
you know, the baseball scandals here and
the, you know, the clear and the the
cream and all that all that stuff. So he
had some um, you know, some interesting
talks about the, you know, about the
history of all of it. Um, he was a
little bit skeptical. Well, I think we
were on the same page about being, you
know, feeling great and optimistic at
the beginning of the, you know,
beginning of the talk and man, these
guys are really great. They came out
really strong, including, you know, the
spokesman for the FDA. Like, those are
strong words, pro protestosterone.
Then we get to the end and some of the
um, you know, some of the the regulators
who are actually involved in how the
policies change and what has to actually
happen really kind of just, you know,
they were kind of a buzzkill. You know,
they were they were the party pooper.
They're like, "Man, you know, we need
some more research and we need this and
that." And, you know, we just spent an
hour hearing about all this great
research um you know, about how all the
research done is basically with an aging
population and it's shown all these
fantastic benefits from them, you know,
for them. And then this, you know, this
gentleman comes out and says, "Hey, you
know, we can't make any big decisions.
We're just here to listen and let's
let's see what we can do. We'll see what
the research says and you know, before
we can make any kind of label changes."
So, uh, that that was a little bit of a
buzzkill. And Rick had seemed to have
kind of that same, you know, that same
thought. So, he was cautiously
optimistic. Um, he had a really
interesting, you know, perspective,
though, too. So, we're back to that, you
know, it's a scheduled substance and
it's illegal. So, you know, your
doctor's worried about getting in
trouble with the law and with their
license for prescribing this stuff. Um,
and then people will take things in
their own hands, right? They see like, I
really think I would benefit from this.
and they go out and we hear about guys,
you know, underground labs and they buy
they're buying steroids and, you know,
things other than testosterone and doing
all this. Um, but he he's represented
folks who, you know, they're trying to
just treat their own, you know, do their
own TRT. So, they seek out this stuff
when their doctor turns them down and
now they have this controlled substance
obtained illegally and now they're in
trouble. Now, they have to call this guy
and they're spending money. They're in
legal trouble. It, you know, it turns
their lives upside down. She's had a few
unfortunate cases like that. Um, and it
was interesting because I I actually
have had some patients come to me who
have been self- treating like that,
right? You think you hear, "Oh, you've
been taking some underground stuff, man.
This guy's been blasting roids and, you
know, he's going to be a mass monster
and all this stuff." That's not, you
know, it hasn't been the case with these
guys are coming to me. I'm seeing guys
in their 50s and 60s that, you know,
they had a bad talk with their PCP. They
heard about this stuff. They got it
online and they're doing reasonable
protocols, right? right? They're taking,
you know, 150 milligrams per week in
divided doses and doing all the things
we advocate for. The only problem is is
again they're breaking the law buying
this stuff and who knows what they're
actually getting, right? So they have
this, you know, they have this
underground stuff that's of questionable
quality.
So that's a so that's a problem and I
think it's something else and it's a big
reason to deschedu this. We have people
get into legal trouble over this over
this substance. It's uh you know one of
the panelists mentioned that it's um
it's less you know has less addictive um
uh risk than caffeine, right? And then
here we are here we are people getting
in legal trouble and and having a having
a hard time getting this stuff.
>> So that's a real it's a real shame.
>> Yeah. Well, testosterone is still our
own uh manly hormone while caffeine is
still um yeah a foreign substance for
our body. And the same goes for a lot of
um drugs like SSRIs and so on. General
practitioners they rather prescribe
SSRIs because young men are depressed
instead of their own hormone which they
are lacking. So that's just mind-blowing
sometimes.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And they even brought that
up a little bit in in the meeting too.
They were talking about mental health,
you know, the mental men's health crisis
in general, but mental health and you
know, the importance of of fixing
hormones for, you know, for correcting
that. Uh, I thought that was a very, you
know, a very important point and there's
there's definitely better ways to do it
than throwing some, you know, some
outside chemical. Let's work with our
own, you know, what we already have.
Let's maybe top top it off a little bit
and see what we can do.
>> Yeah. Um, sometimes I see patients in my
practice become because they they come
for acne seeing me and they are on
terrible TRT protocols. they get from
their GP. Sometimes 250 milligrams of
testosterone, one shot every two or
three weeks even. Some of them get
nibbido. So that's one shot of 1,000
milligrams every three months. All
protocols like that. And then they do
their own research online. They see they
should get one or two injections per
week and then they they buy stuff
underground. It's just the same thing
like you mentioned.
>> Yeah. Yeah. It's too bad. It's too bad.
I mean in a the the way the system
should work is you should be able to go
and have an honest, you know, an honest
talk with your doctor. And even if, you
know, even if they're not fully on board
with it, the idea of a, you know, a
health criminal, we don't, you know, we
don't talk about that with other things
in medicine. You know, someone who's an
actual drug addict comes in, they're
addicted to opioids, we don't just we
don't just shun him and throw him out.
We try to help them. So, it's a little
it's crazy the the stigma behind all
this. So hope hopefully some of that
starts to die starting with this, you
know, with this meeting and the more we
could talk about this, uh, which is
another reason I wanted to talk to you
today. The more, you know, the more we
could get this out there, let's uh,
let's put an end let's put an end to
this and see what we can see what we can
do.
>> Okay, sure thing. Uh, any other takeaway
points from this um, FDA panel on DRT?
>> Yeah, so you know, there's a there's a
couple of a couple of things here. You
know, I have some I have some of the
quotes from some of the, you know, some
of the uh the panelists in here. Let me
see if I can if I can pull them up here.
Um, so there's a there's a lot of talk
in there about, you know, testosterone
being a um a lifestyle drug, right?
That's that was kind of kind of the
biggest, you know, the biggest pushes
there is, you know, it's a lifestyle
drug. It's for cheating in sports. It's
for vanity only. Um, you know, so you
one of the, you know, one of the
panelists who's a, you know, she's a
she's a clinician. which is, you know,
testosterone therapy is not a lifestyle
drug. It's a cornerstone of preventative
health, a therapy that restores health,
function, and longevity. Uh, so I think,
you know, a re, you know, a reframe of
of all that is a is a is a smart is a
smart thing. Um, you know, we were
talking there there's a lot of talk
about how testosterone can actually
increase um, uh, longevity and improve
health span. So, it improves all the,
you know, all the markers of aging. And
this is this is covered in depth in here
by multiple you know multiple members of
the panel.
>> We see improvements in you know decrease
in obesity improvements in in uh
diabetes um bone density reduce and
reduce fractures reduction in sarcopenia
or muscle loss. So these are all you
know all aspects of aging that are going
to either you know make a difference how
your you know how your years are going
to go how your older years are going to
be if you're going to be active and uh
you know able to participate and enjoy
that time or not. [snorts]
But the current labeling says, you know,
it's not an indication to be used for
aging. So unless you have some real
specific, you know, you're either, you
know, dead on primary or secondary
hypogonatism, these in between things
aren't, uh, you know, aren't as
important. And that was one of the, you
know, one of the, you know, the the buzz
kills from the, uh, you know, the FDA
official. He actually came out and said,
hey, you know, things like, you know,
um, indications like fatigue, you know,
can't be can't be a thing. You can't say
you have fatigue and low testosterone.
That's just not that's just not enough.
>> It's not I don't know. That sounds
pretty good to me. Right. If we can fix
you and now you feel better and you're
you're getting you're getting stuff, you
know, you're getting stuff done.
>> Um but I think, you know, back back to
some of the you know, some of the
history on this thing too when they
opened up. It's one of the first times
this has been acknowledged too is that,
you know, this was done for purely
political reasons, right? Right. So in
1988 um the Olympics Ben Johnson
Canadian sprinter he um uh you know won
I think it was the 100 meter and set a
world record right and then he tested
positive for uh for winstrol which is a
steroid right which ironically is not
testosterone right so he didn't even
test positive for testosterone
>> so you know congress got very upset um
you know the government was very all
worked up hey we must end cheating in
sports we must protect the children and
then you know moving forward from there
you know with a lot of steam came they u
you know they passed the 1990 um you
know steroid act that made all this you
know all this stuff um controlled
including testosterone but the you know
the more interesting part there was that
they had you know they they asked for
witnesses before this they asked for
expert expert witnesses right so they
had they actually had someone from the
FDA come to Congress and say don't
schedule this it's not appropriate you
don't need to do this they have someone
from the DEA come in and say you know
don't do this this isn't the way to do
someone from the American Medical
Association. Um, and there were sever
several other groups, too. So, they had
all the all the experts they asked said,
"Don't do this. This isn't what you need
to do." And then what did the government
do? They did it anyway, right? They
already had a preconceived notion. They
had a plan and, you know, we must
protect the children and off we go. So,
you know, it must, you know, must
protect sports.
>> Yeah.
>> And then these all these years later,
they're trying to undo it. So, my point
there is I hope they do listen to the
experts this time,
>> right? So, I mean, you asked the experts
last time, you didn't listen. So, if
we're going to have another chance this
time, please, you know, please do please
do listen. Um, I I think that would be,
you know, that's a real a real important
point and I hope they hope they take
that into consideration.
>> Yeah, sure. Yeah, it's incredible here
too in I said before, they all throw it
on the same heap. It's all the same
thing. Uh, Winstrol, anabolics, TRT. Uh
e even general practitioners they they
don't make uh any distinction between
the two.
>> Sure.
>> Yeah. It's a strange time to to to live
in. They they say, "Oh, you're on
steroids." But they they get this 13
year old girls on anticonceptive pills
just uh because of their acne, for
example,
>> and they think that that is normal.
>> Yeah.
>> No, it's absurd. It's absurd. Even back
to the, you know, even back to the
lifestyle part about it. We were we were
chatting about this a little bit too.
Another thing we were talking with Rick,
you know, Rick Collins about is um you
know, they say, "Hey, it's not a
lifestyle thing. It's not for
cosmetics." But in 2025, I mean, even if
it was just for that, who cares? Yeah.
>> How about that, right? I mean, you can
do you can get Botox for your face. You
can get plastic surgery and get, you
know, I'm allowed to go get calf
implants if I want to. But if I want to,
uh, you know, if I want to get my calves
back to the size they were when I was 20
because I'm losing some muscle mass, I
can't do that. But I can go I could go
get a dangerous surgery.
>> Meanwhile, I'm not allowed to take this
medication that has proven health
benefits, is going to help me live
longer in general, and actually has some
functional muscle. Yeah.
>> So, that's a little bit a little bit
crazy and it doesn't really uh it
doesn't make a whole lot of sense, but
it just goes back to show it's just
purely uh you know, it's been purely a
political a political thing.
>> Mhm.
>> Yeah. And I think, you know, before I
forget too, one of the other interesting
points I noted too was um you know, the
FDA said that the process of doing this
always includes, you know, some
sponsorship from uh from a
pharmaceutical company, right? By
sponsorship, I mean, you know, some
involvement and they have to kind of
lead the charge and give them some ideas
because the FDA doesn't have all the
information and they need some, you
know, need someone to kind of kind of
help lead the way. Uh, so they put it
out there and said, "Hey, you know, we
really need some, you know, really need
some folks to do that." Um, and I did
note that, you know, some of the members
of the panel, and they were all great,
too. They all had great things to say.
basically they're very focused on
patients but they're [clears throat]
also involved in companies that um
either uh you know they use testosterone
gels or long acting testosterone on
deckate injections or oral testosterone
on deckate you know some oral some oral
preparations. So it makes me kind of
wonder is that something that's going to
be pushed more than some of these other
known things that we know to work well.
I would have liked to hear them address
things about, you know, how about uh,
you know, compounded medications. What
do you think about um, you know,
compounded cream or, you know, even
compounded injectable testosterone?
I don't think I think it's going to be
quite a stretch to have the government
go for, you know, back back that kind of
thing. But it was it was curious to see
that um, you know, the folks who were
there did kind of represent those, you
know, those companies. Mhm.
>> Um and and that part of that could be,
you know, they they want that to be on
board because they're seen as things
that have less less abuse potential,
right? You're not going to bathe
yourself in jail and get, you know,
total testosterone of 2500 out of that
or you're not going to take, you know,
oral testosterone a decanate. You you
can actually I have a few guys who have
some decent levels on that, but they're
not going to get, you know, crazy
high-end or, you know, really fantastic
results probably.
>> Yeah.
>> So, that was uh that that was an
interesting point. I'd like to see where
where all that goes too.
>> Yeah. Talking about that, uh I don't
know where these laws come from, but
like here in Belgium, a pharmacist can
not compound a higher concentration of
testosterone than 4%.
>> Yeah. Four. So
>> that's crazy.
>> Yeah. When I started compounded TRT
cream back in 2017, I was recommended by
one of your American colleagues to to
have a 20% cream made. He gave me the
formula. I asked that to my personal uh
pharmacist here and he made that for me
and I was happy with it and I reordered
and reordered and all of a sudden he
said, "Oh, Stephen, I I cannot make that
for you anymore." I said, "Why?" Yeah, I
I looked it up and there are laws that
forbid to compound higher than 4% in
Belgium.
>> I don't know who invented that law just
to prevent abuse as you just said, but
what you got to do
>> almost a good enough almost a good
enough concentration for a woman.
>> Yeah,
>> right.
>> that's crazy.
>> Yeah, that's crazy. Oh yeah,
>> we so so we can order it online in an
international compounding pharmacy and
have it sent to us. That that's
completely legal, but you cannot order
it in a a local pharmacy here in
Belgium.
>> Yeah, that's crazy. Well, there's some
other laws like that too in in other
European countries too, I think. Right.
Like you're you're allowed to possess
but you're not allowed to sell or that
kind of thing too, right? So there's a
little
>> some some gray areas there.
>> Yeah. Like for like for weed and
cannabis, it's all all those mixed sil
you you you you can use it and you you
can possess it but you cannot buy it.
>> Mhm.
>> So where do you get it? So it's all
>> right. Right. [laughter] Right.
>> Yeah. And I kind of I was wondering a
little about that that you know with
that too you know here there's been a
lot of change with marijuana laws. Um
and it was just I think there was just
so much pressure like hey everyone's
everyone's kind of doing it. It's
everywhere. Are we going to arrest
everyone? Yeah.
>> So, I kind of wonder with the, you know,
with the testosterone thing if that's
getting to be the same kind of thing
like, ah, you know, do we really need to
need to be illegal anymore?
>> I don't know.
>> Yeah. Let's hope so. One day that it's
uh yeah, that it can be just uh used by
everyone and those stupid laws uh yeah
are abolished.
>> I hope so. I hope so.
>> Yeah.
>> But yeah, I think I think overall I
think this was a you know, a great
panel. It's a good it's a good listen.
Definitely, you know, definitely check
it out. Um, I don't know what the next
step will be here. Hopefully it doesn't
take him another, you know, another 40
years to do something.
>> Yeah, let's hope they have another talk
next year with some improvements.
>> Yeah, I hope so. I hope, you know,
hopefully they invite some other some
other experts back. It would have been
nice to see um, you know, some some
folks from our community, right? I'd
like to see, you know, Rick Collins on
that board would be great. I think, uh,
you know, Dr. Jordan Grant on there
would be awesome. That would be pretty
pretty cool. Get some good
representatives like that in there. So,
I'm volunteering them. So, there you go.
There you go, guys. Get out there.
[laughter]
>> Okay. Um, any more concluding remarks on
this, Mike?
>> You know, there was
there was one other bit in here, too, I
thought it was interesting. I just
wanted to bring up. Um, Dr. Morgan
Taller, you know, he was kind of
responsible for just really, you know,
spearheading just um dispelling all the
myths about prostate cancer. uh he had
he had a quote in here where he said
that all that research was just based
upon one single patient. That's where it
all stemmed from. One single patient in
and now here we are in 2025
and it's finally, you know, it's still
it's still on the label ready to come
off. All the research has been done, but
just just beaten to death and just
completely wrong and it's gone for that
for that long. Yeah.
>> And it just it's just it's just a you
know, it's absurd.
Yeah. That's how medicine goes. That's
how medicine goes.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So, you know, a little bit
of uh little bit of progress, but we'll
see. We'll see what we get.
>> Yeah. Okay. So, um let's uh look forward
what we're getting uh next year maybe.
And um any uh advice to the the viewers
still uh listening, Mike? I think, you
know, go go watch this thing, share it
with a friend, share it with your
doctor, and let's uh let's, you know,
let's let's spread the word.
>> Okay. Thank you so much for uh breaking
this down. Thank you so much.
>> Yeah, thanks for having me.